Nancy Hamilton Papers, 1862-1992
Sophia Smith Collection
Nancy Hamilton papers
1862-1992
1952-1959
Hamilton, Nancy
MS 189
14 boxes (27 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Playwright, Lyricist, Actress, Producer. Collection includes correspondence; promotional material; scripts (some in braille); photographs; original film footage and soundtrack chiefly relating to filming, production and distribution of the Oscar winning documentary film Helen Keller in Her Story (1955). Included are research files, biographical information, correspondence and other papers relating to Helen Keller, Annie Sullivan, actress Katharine Cornell, Keller's companion Polly Thomson, and her friend Adele Levy. Of particular interest is original film footage from the production, including trims and out-takes, stills, sound recordings, and footage from other sources. Almost half of the footage has been reformatted to DVD and CD for preservation and research use.
Nancy Hamilton, Broadway actress, lyricist, author, scriptwriter, producer, and playwright was born in Sewickley, Pennsylvania, July 27, 1908, daughter of Charles Lee Hamilton and Margaret Miller Marshall. She was educated at Miss Dickinson's School in Sewickley, at the Sorbonne, and received a B.A. from Smith College in 1930. Hamilton began writings songs and sketches while at Smith, acting in and directing The Chocolate Soldier in her senior year. She was Producing Director of the Dramatic Association Council at Smith. After a period of amateur acting and producing in Pittsburgh and Montclair, New Jersey, she moved to New York City in 1932 and leased a large apartment with an assortment of women friends. For a short time she worked for Stern's Department Store and then for RKO Pictures as a spy checking audience reactions and reporting on vaudeville acts. She began her acting career as understudy to Katharine Hepburn in The Warrior's Husband and also had a walk on part in the play. She made her Broadway debut in 1934 in New Faces, not only appearing in the show but also writing many of the lyrics. When it closed she turned to play writing. She collaborated with Rosemary Casey and James Shute on Return Engagement which was made into a film entitled Fools for Scandal. During the next two years Hamilton wrote radio scripts for comic actress Beatrice Lillie, Fred Astaire, and Lois Long, and published articles and poems in Stage Magazine and Harper's Bazaar. She went on to write lyrics for three successful Broadway revues (a genre of musical theater that flourished in the 1930s): One for The Money (1939) ran for 132 performances, Two for the Show (1940) ran for 124 performances, and Three to Make Ready (1946) ran for 323 performances. These revues launched the careers of Alfred Drake, Keenan Wynn, Gene Kelley, Betty Hutton, Eve Arden, and Ray Bolger. Song lyrics written by Hamilton include "How High the Moon," "The House with the Little Red Barn," "The Old Soft Shoe," "I Hate the Spring," "The Old Gavotte," "Lovely Lazy Kind of Day," and "Clambake." In 1945 she spent six months with the American Theater Wing War Players touring the battle areas of France, Italy, Belgium, and the Netherlands. In the mid-1950s Hamilton produced Helen Keller In Her Story (also known as The Unconquered), a documentary on the life of Helen Keller narrated by Katharine Cornell. It won an Academy Award in 1955 for the best documentary.
Nancy Hamilton is known as one of the first women to succeed as a lyricist. Korey Rothman in her dissertation, "Somewhere There's Music: Nancy Hamilton, The Old Girls Network, and the American Musical Theatre of the 1930s and 1940s,"¹ states that Hamilton is "…an important unsung figure of the twentieth century musical theater" and that she "…was part of a large network of women with whom she maintained overlapping professional and romantic relationships." She was the life-long partner of actress Katharine Cornell. Hamilton died in New York City, February 18, 1985, after a long illness.
[¹ PhD Dissertation, University of Maryland at College Park, 2005]
The Nancy Hamilton Papers contain 26 linear feet of correspondence, printed materials, photographs, memorabilia, miscellaneous papers, and sound track and original film footage for Helen Keller in Her Story (1955). The materials are concentrated in the period from 1952 to 1959 when Hamilton developed, produced, and distributed the film. They relate primarily to the film, Helen Keller, and some of Keller's friends and associates. There is no material related to Hamilton's other professional work or her personal life. Of particular interest are 132 reels of original film footage of Helen Keller and others from Helen Keller and Her Story. Almost half of this footage has been reformatted for preservation and research use [see list in Appendix].
Select film and audio clips from this collection have been digitized and are available to view online.
This collection is organized into six series:
I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS AND CORRESPONDENCE
II. HELEN KELLER IN HER STORY
III. SUBJECT FILES
IV. PHOTOGRAPHS AND NEGATIVES
V. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS
VI. OVERSIZE MATERIALS
The Nancy Hamilton Papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection with the following exception: original film footage, audiotapes, and sound recordings are closed.
Research copies of some of the film and sound recordings are available on DVD and audio CD.
Select film and audio clips from this collection have been digitized and are available to view online.
In 1966 Nancy Hamilton, producer of the documentary film Helen Keller in Her Story, gave Smith College all the film footage made during its production in 1952 and 1953. After Hamilton's death in 1985, the Sophia Smith Collection received a bequest of her file of materials concerning the filming of Helen Keller in Her Story.
Academy Awards (Motion pictures); American Foundation for the Blind; Blind -- United States; Blind-deaf -- Education; Blind-deaf -- United States; Burke, Billie, 1884-1970; Documentary films -- United States; Motion pictures -- Awards; Motion pictures -- Distribution; Motion pictures -- Production and direction; Motion pictures -- United States; People with disabilities in motion pictures -- United States; People with disabilities -- United States; People with disabilities -- Education -- United States; Teachers of the blind-deaf -- United States; Theater -- New York (State) -- New York; Universities and colleges -- Massachusetts; Cornell, Katharine, 1893-1974 -- Correspondence; Graham, Martha; Henney, Nella Braddy, 1894-; Keller, Helen, 1880-1968; Levy, Adele Rosenwald, 1892-1960; Shute, James L. -- Correspondence; Sullivan, Anne, 1866-1936; Thomson, Polly; Tyson, Katharine Keller -- Correspondence; Tyson, Mildred Keller -- Correspondence; Wood, Richard Carver -- Correspondence; Helen Keller in her story (Motion picture: 1955) -- Sources; Keller, Helen, 1880-1968--Correspondence
APPENDIX: Digitized film footage
From production footage for Helen Keller in her Story (1955)
Select film and audio clips from this collection have been digitized and are available to view online.
PICTURE ELEMENTS (Part I)
DVD no. Topic Notes on content Run Time (mins)
1 Arcan Ridge Scene cuts: HK walking in garden with dog (retakes); with two children and pumpkin, gifts; HK and another woman (Polly?) working in garden; interior: HK reading braille, and using braille machine. 8:00
1 Arcan Ridge HK in bed. reading Braille; HK and Polly Thompson; HK touching things; Polly packing 7:00
1 Misc HK being given award by woman in uniform (with sound); visiting classroom; signing with students; visiting Korean vets in hospital; using braille(?) machine and signing with group at table 4:00
1 Graham Sev takes of car on highway; Martha Graham studio-complete-Maypole 6:00
1 Graham Martha Graham studio (cont'd): HK speaks to students (sound on disc 5); Dance of Death (1st part) work print (probably scratched) 3:00
1 Graham and other Martha Graham studio (cont'd) -performance; dancers with HK; HK/Polly-- opening scene where HK wishes she could speak better, Polly interpreting 6:00
1 Graham Walking on street to Martha Graham School of Contemporary Dance; in studio, performance retakes; talking with students; in elementary school class; on stage preparing to speak to audience 6:00
1 Swarthout HK reading Braille; Piano (sound on disc 5), Gladys Swarthout singing while HK touches her face (sound disc 5); HK, Polly and 2 men ("theater friends"); Swarthout looking awkward with HK touching her face (before Swarthout starts singing); Polly and HK at Arcan - close-ups 7:00
2 Japan Japan outs: Ike's Japan; ship, Japanese schoolgirls (with sound, Japanese narration) 6:00
2 Japan HK in Japan, full frame (no sound) 9:00
2 Australia Japan Newsreel with sound - Australia, HK speaking with Polly (with sound); Japan 7:00
2 Paris Paris street scenes; with puppy at fountain 1:00
2 Paris Paris (cont'd) with sculptures; street scenes; with young girl; reading book with Polly; at Eiffel Tower 8:00
2 Japan Australia Paris Brief clips (outtakes) from Australian newsreel (some clips with sound), Japan and Paris 7:00
2 S Africa Newsreel composite -- South Africa visit (with sound), beginning with Polly on a ship 5:00
2 S Africa Continuation of newsreel composite -- South Africa vist (with sound), beginning with Polly on a ship 6:00
3 Deliverence Deliverance-clips from film 3:00
3 Deliverence Deliverance (cont'd) 6:00
3 Deliverence Deliverance - out takes Baby trims from the movie 10:00
3 Fox Movietone News Fox Movietone News: "How Helen Keller Learned to Talk"- Annie Sullivan speaking with HK; receiving award (with sound) 3:00
3 Arcan Ridge and misc Takes: HK in garden and interior - typing; with Polly; visiting classrooms; with Korean vets in hospital; HK in front of shops; Martha Graham studio; buying a hat; montage of HK with famous people (opticals/photographs, etc.); HK with Swarthout 8:00
3 Paris; Misc Newsreel outtakes (with sound)-Paris, speaking at the Sorbonne, receiving medal; M. Graham outtakes; Arcan-braille machine; closeup of Braille 3:00
3 Misc " (cont'd) bust of Braille; door knocker opening from Deliverance 0:30
3 Deliverance Cuts from Deliverance 0:30
3 Arcan Ridge and misc Car arriving; playing with dog in yard; Unidentified man; HK at Japanese shrine with Polly and other woman; Hamilton on terrace; HK study; closeup of hands; Braille clock; HK with blind/deaf workers in factory; HK/Polly shopping for hat 7:00
3 Misc Drummer at Martha Graham's (sound on disc 5); HK, Polly and 2 men ("theater friends"); Japan footage; Gladys Swarthout 8:00
4 Misc Small clips from newsreels (some with sound) and original footage- Paris, South Africa; Capitol building; Arcan-- inside house: clothes closet; shopping. 4:00
4 Misc S. Africa and Australia newsreel clips (with sound)-includes HK speaking. blind workers. HK speaking to audience (no sound); shopping; visiting classroom 5:00
4 Misc Still photos--HK, family and others (some famous), homes, plays, books, films, etc. 9:00
4 Misc Trees (Arcan?); stills of HK and others; Shots of letters mailed to HK; Paris and Japan scenes --with young girl in Paris, Japanese train station; Arcan (?) stone wall 7:00
4 Misc Trims/outtakes: arriving at Library of Congress; dinner banquet; giving lecture at Lof C; still photos of HK and others; with children at Arcan; Marths Grahem studio; theater friends; Arcan interior with Polly 7:00
4 Misc Various clips and outtakes - Arcan Ridge exterior; door knocker opening to film; HK reading Braille; with President Eisenhower at the White House (narration on Tape 5, track 7) 5:00
4 Misc 16mm Misc newsreel scenes spliced together-Australia-- HK and Polly speaking demo (only part with sound); Paris--: touching sculptures, with young girl; visiting classroom; giving lecture at LOC. Arcan Ridge-playing with dog, planting mint, with Polly; with bird; reading; 5:00
4 Misc 16mm Paris - with young girl; Arcan ridge-whistling to canary (sound on disc 5); playing with dog. planting mint;; Australia newsreel clips: "Human marvel brings hope to deaf children", visiting classroom, kids playing; Library of Congress; Paris - market, Eiffel Tower, with puppy at fountain, and other scenes, feeling sculptures; With kids in classroom; arriving Australia 13:00
6 Swarthout One of 4 reels from original --Gladys Swarthout singing with HK touching face 1:00
6 Swarthout Sound only - GS singing 1:00
PICTURE ELEMENTS (Part II)
1 Graham Martha Graham studio - 2 dancers 5:30
1 Graham Martha Graham studio 15:00
1 Graham Martha Graham studio 6:25
1 Graham Martha Graham studio 7:30
1 Arcan Arcan Ridge, small scenes (trims): HK's house, 3 at table for lunch, front porch, HK reading, letters; Arcan interiors 9:00
1 Arcan Arcan Ridge exteriors 1:30
1 Arcan Arcan Ridge, small scenes (trims): HK in kitchen, sundeck, closet, exit from house; exteriors of house; Polly/HK at breakfast; some close ups of HK and German shepherd; interior of house: HK and Polly; end credits 7:30
1 Arcan Arcan Ridge, small scenes (continued) 0:30
1 Arcan Polly putting HK to bed; trees; HK hands reading Braille Bible 5:45
1 Arcan (continued) 1:00
1 Arcan continued) 0:15
1 Arcan Arcan Ridge: downstairs; new talking Braille machine; trees 2:15
2 Japan Japanese footage (probably news footage) 18:00
2 Mixed Arcan Ridge (including stone wall); HK learning Braille, typing; trims of scene with children; hands signing Roosevelt; end of Deliverance 3:00
2 Mixed Outtakes-some of it newsreel: HK in Australia 2:30
2 Mixed HK with bird cage 9:00
2 Mixed ? 6:45
2 Mixed HK's Speech, beginning; HK and Polly; exterior Arcan at night; HK close-ups; Veterans in hospital footage 5:30
2 Mixed Still sequence - Swarthout - Lib. Congress, Paris Swarthout; Library of Congress: HK lecturing/talking to people; Paris; bay dock; Coolidg; Native Americans 2:00
2 Mixed (continued) 6:00
3 Mixed (continued...) HK's Speech, beginning; HK and Polly; exterior Arcan at night; HK close-ups; Veterans in hospital footage 1:45
SOUND TRACK ELEMENTS (Part I)
CD # Topic Notes on content Running Time CD Track Number
5 Graham Helen speaking to Martha Graham dancers with Polly translating 2:00 1
5 Graham " (cont'd) 2:00 2
5 Misc Whistling to canary, laughing, voice of director; Piano playing ("Music scene"); "Scene 4C" -- Drummer at Martha Graham's studio "scene C5" -- Piano 10:00 3
5 Graham Music (probably Graham studio?) 0:30 4
5 Swarthout Swarthout singing; HK talking 2:00 5
5 Misc and Cornell narration Newsreel track - Australia; Misc cuts of narration by Katharine Cornell-- Arcan Ridge scenes 2:00 6
5 Cornell narration White House visit narration 1:00 7
5 Cornell narration narration - Library of Congress; on Venereal Disease (several takes) 3:00 8
5 Cornell narration; Graham narration - misc 1:00 9
5 Graham Drummer at Martha Graham's studio 0:30 10
6 (DVD) Swarthout Gladys Swarthout singing 1:00
SOUND TRACK ELEMENTS (Part II)
4 Arcan Arcan Ridge: Polly putting HK to bed; trees; HK hands reading Braille Bible 1:30 1
4 Arcan Arcan Ridge: downstairs; new talking Braille machine; trees 1:15 2
4 Graham Sound. [Martha Graham or narration?] 11:00 3
4 Graham Martha Graham studio 5:00 4
4 Graham Martha Graham studio 10:30 5
4 Cornell Narration by Katharine Cornell - outtakes: The Eldest Child, with Mr. Coolidge. 4:00 6
4 Graham Martha Graham studio - piano/drum 15:00 7
4 Graham Martha Graham studio - piano/drum 18:30 8
4 Mixed HK's Speech, beginning; HK and Polly; exterior Arcan at night; HK close-ups; Veterans in hospital footage 1:00 9
Additional materials about Nancy Hamilton and her professional work may be found in the New York Public Library for the Performing Arts at Lincoln Center. Hamilton also made a film of the twenty-fifth reunion of the Smith College class of 1930. It is available in the Smith College Archives.
The Helen Keller Archives are at the American Foundation for the Blind. Additional Helen Keller materials are at the Perkins School for the Blind, the Alexander Graham Bell Association for the Deaf, and the Library of Congress.
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS AND CORRESPONDENCE 1862-1985, .25 linear ft.
  This series consists of one folder of miscellaneous biographical material related to Nancy Hamilton which includes clippings, articles, and notes (1939-1985). The remaining part of the series consists of general correspondence arranged alphabetically. This is primarily personal correspondence and includes letters from Billie Burke, Douglas Edwards, Dwight D. and Mamie Eisenhower, Helen Hayes, Helen Keller, and Eleanor Roosevelt. There is correspondence from some of the same individuals in SERIES II. HELEN KELLER IN HER STORY. This series also contains a transcript of an 1862 letter from Julia Gardiner Tyler (widow of President John Tyler) to the Commanding Officer of U.S. Forces at Jamestown and Williamsburg. There is no information about how or why this letter is connected to Nancy Hamilton.
- SERIES II. HELEN KELLER IN HER STORY 1919-69, 1.75 linear ft.
  This series consists of six subseries: Development and production, Distribution and showings, Financial and legal matters, Promotion, and Awards and tributes.
  Development and production contains two sections, Source Materials For the Film, and Scripts. The former contains correspondence and notes, particularly from consultant Nella Braddy Henney; Dwight D. Eisenhower regarding his appearance in the film; Rebecca Mack owner of Helen Keller material; and director Richard Carver Wood. Miscellaneous printed material about blindness and undated notes are included as well. The scripts section contains scripts from every stage of filming, including shot sheets and narration scripts for Katharine Cornell. Helen Keller's Braille script is located in SERIES VI. OVERSIZE MATERIAL. Still photographs of Helen Keller's 1919 film, Deliverance, which are part of Development and production, are located in SERIES IV. PHOTOGRAPHS AND NEGATIVES.
  Distribution and Showings consists of correspondence, notes, and clippings about distribution arrangements; problems regarding commercial bookings; and Keller's efforts to promote the film, the proceeds of which were to support services for the blind and the blind-deaf. There are letters and other papers from ABC News, the American Foundation for the Blind, the American Foundation for the Overseas Blind, legal counsel Fitelson and Mayers, and agents Information Productions and Louis de Rochemont Associates. There is also information about special showings of the film, including in Birmingham and Tuscumbia, Alabama, and the Scottish Film Council. In addition there is material regarding showings in foreign countries and in celebration of Keller's seventy-fifth birthday. There is also information about the film's distribution via the United States Information Agency.
  Financial and legal matters contains correspondence, receipts, financial statements, and contracts. These include material from Albert Margolis Co., Information Productions, Louis de Rochemont Associates, Nathan W. Levin, and the American Foundation for the Blind.
  Promotion contains correspondence and other papers regarding publicity and promotion activities, film reviews, and letters of appreciation from viewers. These relate to the film's opening, the "Arlene Francis Show," and miscellaneous promotion events. There is also correspondence, a typescript, and articles related to a Katharine Cornell interview. This section also includes reviews and letters of appreciation.
  Although the film was not a commercial success, it received a number of awards, including an Oscar for best documentary film of 1955. Most of the material in the Awards and tributes section consists of congratulatory and miscellaneous correspondence and printed material related to the Oscar. In addition there is a film of Hamilton receiving the Oscar located in SERIES V. AUDIOVISIUAL MATERIALS. The Oscar statuette and certificate are in SERIES VI. OVERSIZE MATERIAL. There is a small amount of material on an award Hamilton received from Scholastic Teacher and various other tributes.
- SERIES III. SUBJECT FILES 1888-1972, .75 linear ft.
  This series contains correspondence, clippings, articles, notes and other papers that are not about the production of the film. Although the largest amounts of material relate to Katharine Cornell and Helen Keller, there are also documents related to blindness; Brenda Forbes; Adele Levy; The Miracle Worker in which Hamilton invested; Florence Nightingale; the gift of the Hamilton Papers to Smith College, including a report on film footage; Keller's teacher Anne Sullivan, and companion, Polly Thompson.
  The section about Katharine Cornell contains material related to her trusteeship for the American Foundation for the Blind and her support for the American Foundation of the Overseas Blind, as well as an interview with Arlene Francis; correspondence, especially with Helen Keller; and miscellaneous clippings, notes and printed material. The section on Helen Keller includes articles, clippings, awards, medical information, obituaries and materials related to her funeral service, speeches, writings, and transcripts of radio broadcasts. In addition, there are materials regarding proposals to write a biography of Keller; and Keller's seventy-fifth, eightieth and eighty-fifth birthday celebrations; and her overseas tours.
- SERIES IV. PHOTOGRAPHS AND NEGATIVES 1888-1969, .75 linear ft.
  This series consists primarily of photographs and stills related to, and from, Helen Keller In Her Story. These include photographs of Keller alone, mostly undated, that range from her childhood to old age. There are also photographs of Keller with Alexander Graham Bell, Katharine Cornell, her sister Mildred, Anne Sullivan, Polly Thompson, and the Martha Graham Dancers. In addition, there a photographs of Nancy Hamilton, the Keller Homestead, and Anne Sullivan.
- SERIES V. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS 1953-92, 23 linear ft.
  This series contains original film and sound recordings (open reel audiotapes, film soundtracks, and photographs records) most of which relate to Helen Keller In Her Story. There is also a VHS videotape of the documentary. The 132 canisters of original film footage, including 16 and 35 mm prints, trims and out-takes, and footage from other sources are shelved separately. Portions of the film footage and the soundtrack (footage that did not make it into the final version of the film or was used as source material) have been transferred to DVDs for research use [see Appendix]. In addition, this series contains film footage of Nancy Hamilton receiving her Oscar in 1956 and an audiotape of Helen Keller at the Library of Congress in 1992, as well as miscellaneous other sound recordings related to Helen Keller and Helen Keller in Her Story. These items have not been reformatted, but could be on request.
- SERIES VI. OVERSIZE MATERIALS 1952-55, .5 linear ft.
  This series contains two subseries: Photographs and Memorabilia. The Photographs subseries contains two photographs of Keller with Polly Thomson, one with Anne Sullivan, and two with Martha Graham. In addition there is an oversize photograph of a clipping and a photograph of a portrait of Keller in her academic robes. Memorabilia consists of Helen Keller's Braille script and a scrapbook of her seventy-fifth birthday celebration. In addition there are Nancy Hamilton's Golden Reel Award plaque, her Oscar statuette and certificate from the Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences.
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS AND CORRESPONDENCE
  - Articles, clippings, notes, and miscellaneous material, 1939-85, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Miscellaneous, A-Y, 1862, 1952-78, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)